so I was learning to explain anata what
is that
non-self there is no self
there is no self
and what's the point of it like why do
we need to know
[Music]
well you can start by explaining what it
isn't it isn't it is not a denial of
self there is no self because usually
people would basically hear that here
teaching an otter and then end up
naturally jumping into an assumption of
our so there is no real self thus none
of this is real but denying the problem
doesn't actually solve it and especially
doesn't work in this case because the
sense of self it's not about some
metaphysical mistake it's about a
intuitive sense of ownership of your
experience of your senses
and it because of that ownership the
sense of self is generated so the sense
of self in people's lives is not a
problem it's a symptom of an underlying
problem of ownership and if you if you
discern that right order and stop
regarding things as mine and by that I
mean being emotionally connected to them
because that's the ownership it sounds
like you don't care about things that
what that you don't care so if something
happens to those things you won't be
affected so you saying oh that's my mind
makes no difference you want to apply
the attitude of not mine
to the personal emotional level as in
you want to apply it on to things that
you will be affected by if you lose them
if they change against the will so
another is the most fundamental
principle of Buddhist teaching religion
her very first executive that because
there's nothing that you can actually
own in a sense of the you would be its
master control and in charge of and I
will talk about you like the most
fundamental aspects of your experience
so your feelings your perceptions your
intentions are fundamentally given to
you basically they arise and because you
you're not you're not you don't know any
better you just assume that they're mine
because they're here for me who else is
there is just me but that's the problem
with ignorance because there is no there
is no first origin of that mistake it is
a mistake but there is no first point
but that mistake became before which
everything was nice and pure so that
mistake is a starting point which means
you have to accept that there is a
mistake you have to accept it there is a
sense of self that thinks it owns things
but then you you listen to the Buddhist
teaching you read the sutras and you
actually get the sense that it's other
way around it's because you own things
you key predetermine in that sense of
self as that independent order of these
things but it's as I said it's other way
around it's because you keep engaging in
the acts of ownership that sense of self
is being maintained so you stop doing
that and then you then then be enough
the teaching becomes apparent it's not
like there is no self there is no
mistake but you undo the mistake of ownership so
but you undo the mistake of ownership so
then you can truly say there is no self
as in not my own self
so that phenomenon of self still remains
now it's not mine
there is no there is an involvement of
denial of the sense of self
it's basically accepting it as in the
recent phenomena and then I'm doing the
ownership of it so you can truly say
another means that that which is taking
to be myself it's not mine and that
experience is the experience of another
and another thing is basically I think
we spoke about it before actually I
don't know whether it was recorded or
not but all the people would just quote
random science who did everything is
constantly changing does nothing is mine
but that's not enough that it will it
talks about it's that personal side of
ownership that emotional connection to
it so you're not proving any anata if
you say look this stone over there is
comprised of such-and-such minerals and
elements and atoms and atoms and
neutrons and whatever else thus it's not
really it's not really real it's not
really mine but you don't care about it
to begin with so you're not proving
anything because that sense of ownership
it's not an ideology or a order order
order kind of an abstract idea it's
emotional attitude now try and explain
in the same scientific way to your own
daughter or your son or your child your
baby or something you are inherently
bound with emotionally and then see how
indifferent you can remain in fact of
your explanation that is nothing it is
the clump of elements and cells
it's pointless it's completely a flaw
doesn't even apply on the same domain
such explanation which means people use
it only for this ideological purpose to
justify the views but practically
basically the Buddhist teaching frees
you from that emotional dependence
doesn't explain things to you so if if
you think that another is this random
everything is constantly changing and
nothing is mine well it isn't because
that doesn't free
emotional dependence upon those things
so you want to basically find things
that you are emotionally bent upon and
then start undoing the ownership of them
because you see yourself liable to
suffering on account of losing them even
if you don't necessarily lose them and
actually you don't want to wait for them
to be gone to see that you're liable to
suffering of them being gone so that's
what I mean are not the refers to that
personal attitude of something that's
dear to you something that you are
connected with and and I think I think
the etymology of that world
Sanskrit nithya as in Nietzsche sorry
Anita well Anita and Nietzsche as in
Anita Anita and it sounds great but it
was a long time ago since I was looking
for that but there are lots of synonyms
with a word and it can be used basically
for a personal internal dear to me
Nietzsche and then basically uh
Nietzsche would be the opposite of that
so yes you can say it's impermanent but
actually it probably doesn't do it
justice because of well today is modern
contemporary review is what people think
permanence impermanence is this kind of
almost impersonal debate of physics of
how everything is impermanent is
constantly changing but there's just
denial of the existence of the things
that you're emotionally bounded and that
denial can provide people with a relief
with a degree of relief which is what
they mistake it for some sort of truth
because you denying the problem it
covers the problem up but it doesn't
solve it doesn't have root it which
means sooner or later someone you forget
about denying it or something else will
point at it remind you of it and you are
back to square one you haven't made it
made no difference so that's why you
really want to first accept the problem
and stop denying it
and and stop finding justification for
it and that can be helped if you think
that Nietzsche and uh Nietzsche actually
refers to personal and beer and then not
taken personally and not dear to me as
in urine different emotional equilibrium
and there's that simile that the Buddha
gives to the monks he said monks people
get basically upset effected by
suffering when things that they are did
they they're attached to a god are
affected so they should basically
abandon the attachment he doesn't say
they should basically find the
justification for the denial of the
existence of those things and then the
second and then the simile that he gives
he's basically when he says they were
sitting in the in the in the grove in
the forest and he said so for example
see all these sticks and branches just
lying around here and they are
completely indifferent to would you be
upset if some people come here and start
breaking these branches and taking them
and burning them they say we wouldn't of
course we wouldn't because we have
completely emotional indifferent these
branches are nothing to me says well
that's how you should then cultivate the
same attitude towards your own body
toward your own senses towards your own
life but he didn't say that's how you
should start dismissing your own body
and saying well it's not really real and
whatever else because they would just be
obscuring the problem so yes you want
the attitude of completely indifferent
economist in regard to your own
existence your own senses your own your
own thoughts basically your own feelings
but that cannot be done if you keep
denying those thoughts and feeling or
for explaining them is some sort of
ideological terms such as like a
scientific scientific take but other
people say oh yes the the modern science
is proving that the Buddha was right if
the modern science were proving that the
Buddha is right means that every modern
scientist who one takes in that view
would be at least a sort of animal or
even more but the fact that they're not
means they don't know what the camera is
so they cannot even accidentally prove
it and furthermore science is directly
divorced from any phenomenological proof
of the Buddhist teaching because science
inherently negates the existence of
observer of the subject of the personal
point of view science inherently
operates under the assumption of a
public world independent of all of us
failing to see that that's a point of
view that you are completely bound up
with and you cannot step outside of it
which means if you engage in science on
account of trying to understand the
Buddhist teaching or if you engage in a
scientific view basically you're
engaging the view of the denial of the
problem of the personality personal
attachment craving in regard to your
feelings and all of that because then
you're just explaining what's happening
you're not really rooting it through
understanding which is already what sort
of honor begins to do
it's a similar action to that I got it I
got a I got a book I want to read that
bit it's quite connected to that whole
denial it's when people like that
they're the symbol is in the suit as
well where people would say Garin said
well this body is made out of out of
various organs and parts that you know
when they break break down there won't
be any life left there won't be any any
body remaining thus there is nothing for
me to take there to be mine now people
again it's easy to miss read that
because the point is subtle so people
would then think ah things that the made
out of parts are not real so there's the
famous do the questions of the King will
in the wind when he says well it's it's
like a like a having having a chariot
that is made out of parts and if you
take the charity of the park you have
all these random parts thus cheerio
doesn't really exist but that argument
fails to see that the chariot is already
a particular functional assembling of
parts and if you don't call it chariot
you can call it an assembly of parts and
that's a completely valid reality and
valid truth and he was never the problem
but because the problem is after the
problem is not in the things that you
own it's not in the conventions or audio
designations the problem is in your
attitude towards it as in attitude of
appropriation and assumption that's why
the way they said the five aggregates
are not up Adana five aggregates are not
assumption and attachment but there is
no attachment without the five
aggregates but these questions of
kingman linden he actually goes in
explaining that see five aggregates can
actually be broken into parts thus there
is no real person there but that is
putting the problem of ownership putting
the problem of attachment into the five
aggregates and then destroying the 500
you destroy the problem but a buddha
himself said the problem is not in it
it's in regard to it desiring lost in
regard to the five aggregates the
attachment to your experience is there
so that's what I mean like using that
kind of argument just obscures the
problem doesn't solve it denial of the
reality doesn't solve your attachment to
it because then you become attached to
the reality of that denial and you just
obscure it when you read in the sutras
when the Buddha would encourage people
to investigate
well not investigate but really
contemplate the various parts of your
body as in a basis for for experiencing
unknown attraction and repulsion that's
basically to undermine your gratuitous
notion of bodies beautiful oath to
undermine you've the truest notion of
you are in control like you're the
master of this body so you in order to
practice that contemplation rightly you
need to do it on the basis of that body
that has arisen on the basis of that
ownership of your body which means you
need to start seeing these parts of the
body within that single unit of the
functional arrangement that your body is
because by seeing that there are parts
of this functional arrangement of unit
of the body that I own you can see that
actually that ownership is gratuitous
it's not that that body is not real the
ownership is Rashida's because this
thing that I own that I think I'm the
full master controller is fully
determined by these random things that I
can't even access for example your
beating heart like I see even even the
expression my beating heart you kind of
assume the ownership because it belongs
to this body that you own now you trying
to say oh well see this heart is on its
own operates on its own if it stops my
life is gone that's so true but if you
use that argument to say that thus there
is really no body there it's just these
parts well they're just obscuring the
issue because there is the body there
because otherwise if there is nothing
there how can you even direct your
denial at it it has to be there to some
extent and that extent is the functional
arrangement of the body that is actually
comprised out of individual independent
parts not me and my sense of self and my
sense of mastery in my
and thought so yes it's mentioned in the
suitors often this kind of deflection of
for various bodily parts but then it
needs to be done correctly needs to be
done on the basis of the body so that
then you can remove that which is not
necessary in regards to that experience
and that is your own ownership of it
your gratuitous assumption of mastery of
your life but fundamentally even like
biological my own heart but if it were
yours you would be able to tell it when
to beat and hard to beat
you wouldn't be completely left out
pushed outside of it
you can't even access the notion of
voluntarily controlling your heart yet
if that random pumping muscle in your
chest stops your lives gone that is yet
at the same time you maintain the full
notion of mastery over your life so
looking at the heart the heart is just
if done correctly will up true that you
can sure it was master it will not deny
that the reality of your life and that's
why other hand who is who is fully
approved to that and enlightened person
who is fully Buddha he still operates
normally seemingly from external point
of view he has intentions he has choices
he has decisions all all that states
what he doesn't have is the ownership of
the five RS he doesn't have the the
ownership of the experience as a whole
he doesn't own his body he doesn't own
his intentions doesn't mean his and the
only way to arrive basically and that
point of not ownership is to first
accept it
hence the accepting of responsibility
for your own actions
accepting the validity basically of
actions of the results of actions of the
results of practice needs to be the
first step that's the mundane right view
but if you keep denying it as it's not
real you are denying the basis for your
practice
it's very easy to to denying the problem
is myself it's simpler for me it's the
most natural it's the most natural
reaction which is good but it's bound to
the most fundamental attitude that the
Buddha will describe it when there is a
pleasure affirm it further that's how
people yet when they when the people
when people experience the unpleasant
attitude deny it
try to get rid of it remove it and
that's like craving in regard to
pleasant craving in regard to unpleasant
so so so in this particular instance you
realize that there is a problem there is
a problem of the gratuitous sense itself
the things it's a master and owner yet
the the experience keeps keeps
contradicting it because you the
suffering the discrepancy of experience
in suffering should be enough for an
authentic transparent person to see that
actually you are not in control and
yoghurt should gradually this notion of
control it's the reason for your suffering you
it's the reason for your suffering you
are the one responsible for the
discrepancy of your resistance the damn
results in suffering or results in lie
up in inserting in here in being liable
to suffer it results in possibility to
suffer possibility to be affected by
suffering and that in itself recognition
of that is what suffering is
what about seeing yourself
learn seeing yourself not Ricky seeing
your sense of self directly when you
come because you'll be seeing it with
your sense of self as in you'll be
appropriate in that in that portray the
sense of mastery over the sense of self
which means the sense of self it's all
that taught me that's what I said it's
it's a symptom it's not an issue that
you can see and then directly address
it's a symptom called back so if you you
have to start looking at it as such is
if you blame the symptom for the illness
you're not going to see the illness that
undermines it that underlies it sorry so
you have to recognize that you can't
access that sense of self directly
because it's done with the notion of
self which means your senses you might
think oh this is my self and that means
that you're they'll graduate the sense
of ownership in regards to that
experience is it the background of it
it's always elsewhere from where you
look so you have to stop trying to
expect you're gonna find it through like
looking and spotting where it is because
you don't need to you once you reckon is
it's a symptom okay so you stop trying
to chase the symptom you use it as a
criteria whether the illness is still
present and that illness is the sense of
ownership of things that you do have
said that you can kind of experience and
relate to directly such as I choose
sensuality I choose your will I choose this over
I choose your will I choose this over
this because I'm purely acting out of
desire for pleasure desire and lust in
regard to the five aggregates that's
what it will describe that's why the you
Padano in the ultimate to put on at the
ultimate attachment is the attachment of
yourself that's just the he picking lady
stop marking the ultimate the ultimate
apirana is the anticodon of the self
view and so you maintained basically
that symptom as in because you keep
engaging in that which is keeping you
sick you keep maintaining your desire and
you keep maintaining your desire and
lost in your experience and that's
something that you knowingly do
so that's the problem even people who
kind of are familiar with the Buddhist
practice they're aware of the sense of
self they are aware that it's supposed
to be seen as not myself as in anata but
they don't see the study the connection
so then they just keep trying to deny
this sense of self trying to like or not
mine not mine not mine not mine
and address it on its own terms failing
to see basically that it's their desire
and lust they're fully aware in regard
to other things throughout their life
that's the connection that they're
missing and that's why because of that
the whole in the sense of the sense
restraint and sealion virtue comes first
that you can't possibly not be
perpetuating desire and lost in your
thoughts when your physical actions and
verbal actions are fully engaged in it
you can think your thoughts are pure as
much as you want but they're not because
your behavior is still perpetuating that
a mistaken pattern so you have to start
restraining it on that level so that
then it can you can become clearly
visible on the level of your watch Hey
so that's what I mean you rep you have
to see the connection between these
things as in your circuitry the sense of
ownership is maintained through your
careless giving into the desire giving
into the ill-will giving into the
distraction giving into the unwholesome
States in your daily experience and
that's where the practice is being
watchful of those things now being world
full of everything and nothing or trying
to catch your sense of self but trying
to catch a perfect moment that will
reveal that nothing is real thus there
is no self really no none of that was
ever a problem the only problem is you
engaging in unwholesome and that's why
it's defined as unwholesome because it
keeps it's a direct determination of the
of the problem of suffering of the
problem of gratuitous ownership and
mastery of your experience that's why
it's unwholesome
if he doesn't partake in that it's not
unwholesome which means it's either
neutral for each other also
hey shut it
no flavour job is healthy
so what happens then when you no longer
own that sense of self well that's a
true definition of freedom you you you
you have basically laid down the burden
the burden erection the burden of you
have lay down the liability to suffer
Jesus cannot affect you and that's the
direct measure of that freedom inability
to suffer amid suffer
that sounds like the kind of madness
like somebody well you're nice right
well no see that's it that's what I mean
that's why I keep saying you have to
start with non-denial is it to the
result exactly in that people doing all
sorts of horrendous things and then
saying well there is really nobody there
which was exactly one of the wrong views
that the Buddha was criticizing
back that back in the day when in India
they believed and actually I read that
there was in bhagavad-gita was the whole
point of saying nobody you can go and
kill you can chop people's heads off and
nobody gets he'll killed is just the
sword running through the elements and
whatnot and the Buddha criticized that
is extremely wrong view they can result
in a lot of suffering for you if you
have doubt of it see that's when you
basically jump to a conclusion not
develop the understanding of the
conclusion and if you actually look
closer to this conclusion you realize
okay in order to understand it I must
stop denying things I must accept that
human life is a real thing a choice is a
real thing the body it's a reality as
such things appear differently but they
are real in whatever manner they appear
so even a pure abstract thought it is
real as an abstract thought that's the
definition of phenomenology as in
basically understanding of phenomenon
the standing of appearance but people
get a hint of it maybe are there is
really no self they find their view
pleasing without any understanding of it
and that's when they develop these
conclusions are so I can do whatever I
want because there's nobody there is no
doer there and there is nobody who
receives that doing either
he's nobody affected and that was
exactly the view when the
in the time of the Buddha and before and
obviously after whereby you can say
things such as no no it's you do to go
and kill these people you can go and
kill them and nobody gets killed anyway
we are all already divine and saved and
whatnot so that's what I mean the denial
must stop first in order for basis of
understanding to arise besar can us
understand the ownership of something
that you appropriate is yours if you
keep denying that you appropriated
anything oh when are you gonna give me
back I don't know this books I lend you for
I don't know this books I lend you for
books there are no books books don't
exist what you're talking about
no you took it and in this case it's
even worse because you keep taking it
that which is not yours you keep
regarding it as mind there is the real
who is the real and
well the real the question of a real
owner is based on the already that
misperceived owner that you are as in
okay so if I'm not the owner who's the
real owner and that's exactly again
another view back in India that's very
prevalent today the greater sense of
self you abandon your sense of self by
surrounding it - the greater sense of
self but the slightest notion of the
sense of self
you can only relate to because you're
maintaining it on your own self level as
in if you abandon your sense of self
truly if you see this thoroughly and
ownable so to speak totally independent of you
so to speak totally independent of you
because it depends upon things that you
cannot even access let alone control and
tell them what to do
notion any extension of that sense of
self is seen under the same nature not
mine not for me not myself so if people
can conceive and conceive and act out of
the greater sense of self as in God for
example they do so based on their very
personal sense of self and that's why
that's why Sartre meant in basically
that the most common idea of God is just
the extension it's basically if the
ideal of your sense of self being the
ultimate master creator then you project
into this outer universe of the great
the great God being of God or whatever
the mystic energy and so on all of that
is is relatable only through your sense
of self and that's another thing you can
either deny your sense of self try to
get rid of it which fails all you can
try to envelope it in a greater sense of
self which is just again just extension
proliferation of it which is even worse
because it's another way for disputing
your own sense of self
same ability was God's will and so you
decided you decided that what you've
done was actually rooted in the greater
sense of self because yeah truly
intentions arise on their own but you
are the one who chooses to act upon them
intentions present themselves you see a
cup you can use it for drinking you can
use it to throwing chasing chasing
chasing I don't know chasing a wild
animal you can use it for all these
sorts of things it's an object that has
all this intentionality implied in it
but you choose to use it in a certain
manner on account of whatever you're
trying to achieve but then dismissing
the basically dismissing the the reality
of the cup or the object you chose to
use you hope to cover up your
responsibility for the choice of that
thing and that's something you can do or
ascribing the the intention the
intentionality of an object to a greater
God and then saying well see these
things were presented to me in all this
manner that's why I used it it's on my
fault yeah it's not your fault that
things were presented in a manner of
options but it is your fault to choose
to act upon it irresponsibly and denied
the responsibility or act either greed
aversion delusion that's what I mean
denial must stop because as long as you
deny things you interfere with that
which is actually not on you
arising of the thoughts arising of the
options arising of the intentions but
you then choosing to act in a certain
manner on account of this sort on
account of that that's on you and that's
why the Buddha would say all he teaches
basically is suffering in freedom from
it in a sense of by avoiding unwholesome
cultivate the wholesome because it's not
unwholesome to have a thought of
throwing this object at somebody
but if you does not relishing their
thoughts and thinking upon it further
intentionally now that wit is
unwholesome and that's on you or even
worse if you choose them to to verbally
start acting upon it in an abusive
manner and then physically start abusing
somebody while that's of course that's
just the further proliferation of that
unwholesome attitude so that's what I
mean the responsibility must be taken
first the denial of things must be must
be basically abandoned and then you
created the basis for the practice of
Dhamma and that's why it's a middle way
because you don't go and deny everything
or affirm everything you recognize where
the line is where your responsibility
begins and where it ends and you start
thinking like that you can make sense
out of what other hundreds because
people would often like what Aaron is
this like thoughtless basically robot
who just act so automatic no he's just a
person who has basically removed any
ownership and appropriation and
interference from things that arise
naturally which means he's incapable of
acting unwholesome it doesn't mean that
whatever he does or says will be
pleasing to people it means that he
cannot be rooted in greed aversion
delusion cannot be rooted in a wrong
view
come here boy
come in hey Joe focus sit
focus sit
good boy oh you know job but you're a
good girl I wanted to go down there that
fence fixed
it's been practical terms in ultimately
all a person will need to do really is
keep an eye on their own intentions
motivation is what makes them act
because that's what determines wholesome
or unwholesome and then how also more
power also you can do and that's something you
also you can do and that's something you
cannot not be aware of and mindfulness
system is something you can't have too
much of as a willing to describe it's
not so like a raging make any
observation of moment to moment you know
it's awareness of that which is already
present fundamentally intentions
because if you're mindful basically of
the of your body being you're mindful of
your situation that's already
intentional if you're mindful of your
feelings you're mindful of the situation
that's already intentional which means
you have been mindful not not
necessarily to the full extent that's
what I'm gonna say
mindfulness developed to the extent
necessary for the final knowledge but
the possibility of you being mindful it
is always there because these things are
present so that means you can actually
then discern the background of whatever
your situation is which is already that
background is partially you can then
discern the southland motivation behind
your actions and if you desert it you
will see if it's also around also is
this rooted in in desire sensuality
greed aversion is this rooted really in
her will desire to harm or something
what is genuinely rooted in in in in in
good in non-greed non aversion and if
once you discern it you'll be able to
then not act ugly and that's all you
need to do you don't need to try to get
the reader the possibilities of
unwholesome they're just part of how
things arise you can use it for good or
for bad responsibilities on your choice
hard to use it not on the possibility of
how it can be used but none of that can
become a parent if you're just sort of
completely if you have a completely
obscured that's responsibility of your own choice
that's responsibility of your own choice
there hosting that unwholesome and you
obscured it through denying or to
project thing is also someone else
someone else's fault it states the God's
will and everything
say even if it's God's will to present
you with a certain choice she can't make
you choose this a over B that's why the
early extension philosophy said it's not
that in the phenomenal phenomenology and
phenomenological method it's it's
atheistic or anything like that it's
basically just recognizing the fact that
God has no power over your choice so you
can allow the gods to exist as much as
you want but none of the gods can tell
you how to choose you are the one who
chooses what God told you to act upon it
which means whether things come your way
out of complete circumstance the
randomness accident God's will previews
action previous karma and the park and
where else makes no difference because
you presently are responsible for
choosing how to act upon it all this is
because of the a lot of so sorry I've
done this because of that no because
you've done that because you chose this
to be the reason for it
because you can always say no to
everything or yes a bit which means you
can always do the opposite of whatever
is presented to it means the choice is
always a new that's why they hold the
finishin in the in the philosophy was
basically men is condemned to be free
but you cannot not choose and sometimes
people think if I abstain from choice I
didn't choose but abstaining from choice
it's another choice you just chose that
and that's why the Buddha said the being
means exactly this basically beings are
bound with their actions they cannot
escape them as in abstaining from your
action becomes an action for you so the
only way to escape the action is
patrolling first accept it and then see
the degree of your responsibility in it
and stop maintaining that now trying to
overly deny action or overly explain sorry
so in practical terms people want to
meditate and practice correctly in this
manner
always keep a corner of your eye in the
back of your mind basically where your
intentions are and before you do
something checking yourself why why are
you doing it why do you want to do it
you're always getting on sir
it might take a time to cut through all
that like like layers of cover-ups but
it's there you know the truth as we were
discussing before the simile I was
telling you what the example was
brilliant simply good like say say
you're somebody who is on a beautiful
you're somebody who is gonna like a not
necessarily a strict meditation retreat
but say you're practicing seclusion
practicing on distraction and so on and
then you have a thought that arises or I
want to go I want to go to the to the
library in the real monastery and now to
get some suitable so I can read and
study harder now see on the external
based on the external point of view
that's a good thing to do
reading suit does enrich in the basis of
the knowledge contemplation and so on
but that's not a point of view that
matters is the internal point of view
that matters for whoever practices so we
usually want to do notes like try to
justify during pending action based on
the external acceptance of it or denial
of it you want to justify for not based
on the internal reasoning so if you
start looking at why do I really want to
go to the library and take these books
right now wait for a while cause
probably you're not going to get the
answer immediately
but you can then see that oh actually I
want to go because I hope there'll be
some people there and I'll end up being
distracted I'll end up talking to
somebody because I feel a bit well
pressure of doing nothing being alone so
going into into
the group of people can alleviate that
pressure but I can't admit that to
myself directly so I find an excuse for
going to library to take the Suttons
where I know there is a 90% of chance
they will be like-minded people and
they're gonna start talking to me but
that's the whole point then I won't feel
responsible for choosing to distract
myself because well they started talking
to me it would have been rude to just
remain silent but you failed to see that
you already decided to talk to them by
making yourself liable to that
possibility of going in the environment
where there's a good likelihood of
people distracting you from your own
basically self-awareness and solitude
and so on so now you can say well so
I'll never go to library again well
that's also impossible that's also
trying to overdoing you know go to the
library but for the right reasons there
might be a January need to go to library
but it was the unwholesome part of your
mind that made it into the unwholesome
routed it in unwholesome desire because
he has certain things you can abandon
straight away engage with sensuality
sexuality lying stealing you abandon
them there is no wholesome way of doing
that but as the Buddha pointed out there
things such as eating food you can't
stop that because you die but if you eat
it carelessly if you're not aware of
your reasons behind eating the food if
you don't keep those reasons present and
clear if you don't develop clarity in
regard to them inevitably you're gonna
eat out of our agreed and out of
sensuality out of enjoyment for taste
not need for the nutriments and that's
something you have to responsibly
maintain each time you eat the food
and that's the whole point of that
contemplation I will eat for the sake of
health and sustenance of the body
strength so I can continue practicing I
will not eat for notification I will not
eat for sensual enjoyment I will not eat
for taste but that's not something
that's always written like to decide it
for you that's something that you choose
deserve every time you go to eat food so
in this particular instance all you need
to do is be careless for view it in the
boot and immediately become central if
you're not careless it doesn't go into
sensuality but people that's that's
harder to maintain so it's much easier
to then just say are not eat food or not
all eat food that I hate and so on that
doesn't matter you still gonna eat for
unwholesome reasons then because they
are wholesomeness of eating food for
unwholesome reasons it's not in the food
it's in your carelessness so in the
example of going to library no you can
still go to library if you really need
to get the sutras or or other books that
might help you contemplate further but
then you do it very very carefully go to
the hours when you know there won't be
people if there are people are bored
looking at them if you have to look at
them avoid talking to them even at the
sake of being rude and that's how you
know you will not give rise to the
unwholesome but if you just say I'll
never step outside of my house I'm gonna
be locked in this cell for 3 months I
will not talk to anybody ever again
you're just obscuring the problem you're
not gonna see where the line of your
responsibilities while because you're
denying the whole thing that so the
Buddha did make actions and offense to
engage in a practice of silence not
talking to anybody
ever again because they were like those
percent except Romney's they will just
refuse to speak for the rest of their
life you say well it's misguided
but most people would just jump on the
first excuse why do I need to go to
library are because to get in suitors
and that's a good thing okay fine while
the real reason remains underneath right
there and but they refuse to look at it
because then if you feel you will guilt
anxiety sense of responsibility which is
already a burden and that's where the
practice is I'm doing that burden but in
order to do the burden of responsibility
first you need to accept it not